Hello and welcome to Part 1 of the module
on Patterns and Frameworks for Synchronous
Event Handling, Connection Establishment
and Service Initialization.
In this part of the module, we're going to
be presenting the reactor and acceptor
connector patterns, which are key patterns
for event handling, service initialization
and connection establishment.
To motivate these patterns, let's talk a
bit about our expectations of a webserver.
When we talked about the wrapper facade
solution in the previous module we focused
on keeping things simple, we gave you an
iterative solution that doesn't really
scale, its only handling one connection
request, one GET request of the time from
clients which is absolutely not going to
work in practice.
One alternative approach, people have
historically used when they built web
servers, was to be able to support
multiple clients simultaneously.
And a very classic way of doing this is to
use some kind of underlying operating
system IO multiplexer, like select or
poll, or wait for multiple objects.
And to run this in a single thread of
control.
And then to wait for something to happen
on multiple sources of input.
And then to handle all or part of the
incoming request before going on to the
next request from a different client.
Typically when people implement solutions
in this way, they tend to tightly couple a
number of things.
They tend to couple certain concerns.
They couple concerns for event
multiplexing and demultiplexing, service
establishment, connection establishment
and service initialization.
And those things all get glommed together
with the actual protocol processing done
in our case using HTTP.
Lets take a look at little bit of a code
fragment which illustrates these problems.
Here is piece of code you might find in a
traditional, reactive style web server and
what you see it doing as it uses the
select call to wait for.
Either connection events or data events to
occur on multiple sources of handles.
That obviously hard codes us to using
select which may not be the right choice
in all environments and all platforms.
We're also still hard coding ourselves to
some Posix and Unixisms as far as how
socket handles are defined.
That will be a problem if we try to port
to other platforms like Windows.
We're also using sequential linear search
to look through all the handles to find
handles where activity have gotten sources
of events to come in, that will take a
certain amount of long time if there's a
lot of connected clients.
And then finally, we also tightly couple
the protocol processing, the HTTP protocol
processing with the connection
establishment, service initialization, and
event multiplexing.
So how can we get around these problems?
Well what we're going to talk about here
as a way to do it is to apply a pair of
patterns that are often used together.
These patterns are the reactor pattern and
the acceptor connector pattern and we're
going to use these patterns in order to be
able to separate out the generic.
Event infrastructure service
initialization a connection establishment
code from the protocol processing we do in
the web server once things are connected.
Let's talk first about the reactor
pattern.
If you take a look at this diagram, it
illustrates the structure of the reactor
pattern, which is broken up into a couple
of parts.
First we have a role, or a class, called a
reactor.
And it's essentially a container and
applications, or higher level services
register so called event handlers with a
reactor via its register handler methods.
And these handlers are typically pointers
to base class objects that can be
subclassed and customized to provide
specific event handling logic.
The reactor then squirrels away this
information in some internal tables, and
at some point the application turns the
flow of control over to the reactor by
calling it's handle events method or run
event loop method.
At which point the reactor then
coordinates with the underlying IO
multiplexer and synchronous event, the
multiplexing mechanisms that the operating
system provides, which wait for activities
to occur, which wait for events to occur
from different sources of events, on these
handles associated with the event
handlers.
And when stuff happens, it returns and
then the reactor will dispatch the
particular events to the corresponding
event handler by invoking their hook
methods.
Now, the application or the higher level
service will have customized the core
event handler base class.
Overridden its virtual functions.
And then carried out whatever service
specific or application specific
processing functionality is needed to
handle the events.
If you take a look at this paper at this
URL, you'll find more descriptions about
the reactor pattern, and ways to implement
this pattern and practice.
Here's a view that illustrates some of the
dynamics of the reactor pattern.
The dynamics are broken up into a couple
of different phases.
One of the first things we do is we
typically register a bunch of concrete
event handlers with a reactor.
And the reactor often does a little
double-dispatching dance with those event
handlers to get handles and other
information explaining what those Handlers
are trying to do, what types of events
they're concerned with, and those things
get stashed in an internal table.
Then at some point the application turns
the focus of control over to the reactor.
It goes ahead and uses the demultiplexing
and multiplexing mechanisms of the
operating system, to wait for events to
happen, and when those events occur, it
then calls back on the corresponding event
handle.
Note the inversion of control that's
taking place here.
The reactor runs the event loop, it has
the main focus of control and it does
callbacks to hook methods back to the
concrete event handlers to get the work
done.
Let's now turn our attention to the second
pattern in this group of patterns, the
Acceptor-Connector pattern.
The purpose of this pattern is to decouple
the connection establishment and service
initialization lodge, which is fairly
generic as it turns out.
From the more specific customized
application or higher level service
protocol processing that occurs once
things are actually connected.
As with the reactor there's a couple of
layers involved here from a pattern
structure point of view.
The core part of this is some type of
dispatcher.
We're going to be using our reactor,
because they work together nicely.
Which is waiting for say different kinds
of events.
In our particular case, the acceptors and
connectors are concerned with connection
establishment events.
Things that occur when a connection
arrives or when you initiate a connection.
There are several layers on top of the
dispatcher reactor portion, and let's talk
about the most important part.
This is the part that deals with
connection establishment and service
initialization.
In this particular layer, we have three
primary roles, we have connectors,
acceptors and service handlers.
Service handlers are the pieces of logic
that actually carry out the application
protocol.
They have a conversation with their peer.
In our particular case for HTTP, they